<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<blogs>
  <blog>
    <id>1684684979</id>
    <title>Malbog Sulfur Spring</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>Malbog Sulfur Spring is a natural hot spring at the foot of a volcano known as Mount Malindig. It is a stratovolcano in the Buenavista town with an elevation of 1,157 meters above sea level.&#13;
&#13;
Malbog Sulfur Spring nestles within lush greenery surrounded by verdant flora and fauna. Its warm and bluish-white sulfuric water is believed to have therapeutic and healing benefits. The spring has two swimming pools, and both have medicinal properties that can cure skin diseases. &#13;
&#13;
The stream directly comes from the mountain and goes down into a spring pool where tourists can have a rejuvenating dip. Its water is safe to drink and is even believed to cure acute and chronic cases of skin ailments. Some tourists even bring bottles of sulfuric water on their way home.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684685035</id>
    <title>Mongpong Island</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>Off the northeastern coast of Marinduque is Mongpong Island, a charming islet with striking rock formations and a pristine white-sand beach. It has clear blue waters where you can see through colorful reef fishes underwater.&#13;
&#13;
Upon arrival on the island, the Ungab Rock Formation is the first thing that will pique your interest. The huge colossal rock sits on the island’s turquoise waters and white sand. Carved out of the base rock is a triangular hole that forms a land bridge connecting you to the other side of the beach.  &#13;
&#13;
The giant boulder is a sight to behold and a perfect backdrop for your selfies and group photos. Plus, the water underneath the rock arch is shallow, making it a safe spot to swim for kids. The white sand is also a mixture of smooth pebbles and coral fragments.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684685901</id>
    <title>Paadjao falls </title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>While Marinduque is famous for its scenic beaches, there is one enchanting waterfall that stands out from the rest of the Mogpog Marinduque tourist spots, the Paadjao Falls. Situated in Mogpog municipality, the Paadjao Falls is accessible via a 10-minute trek from the highway, which is only 5.5KM away. &#13;
The hidden cascade gently flows from a 15-feet tall rocky cliff down to a 6-feet deep basin with cold and jade-green waters. It majestically nestles underneath the cool shade of verdant greenery and tall trees, making you feel a lot closer to nature. Surrounding the falls are huge and edgy rocks, so be extra careful when crossing the river and falls.&#13;
&#13;
Paadjao Falls is connected to the Mogpog River downstream. It is also an ideal picnic spot where guests can put up tents for camping. Aside from Paadjao Falls, there are other underrated waterfalls in Marinduque such as Norada Falls, Kawa Kawa Falls, and Bulusukan Falls.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684685959</id>
    <title>Marinduque Wildlife Sanctuary </title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>Up next is a piece of greenery that occupies nearly 9,000 hectares of land, the Marinduque Wildlife Sanctuary. It is home to several bird species such as the Zebra Dove, Serpent Eagle, Brahminy Kite, and Philippine Scops Owl. Adding to the lush green landscape are native trees such as Ipil, Narra, Yakal, and Molave.&#13;
&#13;
Inside the wildlife sanctuary are caves that serve as a habitat for rare species, like the cave-dwelling freshwater shrimp. Some wild animals inhabiting the protected land are the Philippine warty pig, the Philippine deer, the cloud rat, and the green racket tail. &#13;
&#13;
The Marinduque Wildlife Sanctuary was declared as a protected land area in 2004 under Presidential Proclamation No. 696. Its forest watershed encompasses the municipalities of Boac, Gasan, Buenavista, Torrijos and Sta. Cruz. The Marinduque Wildlife Sanctuary is a must-visit hiking, camping, and bird-watching spot for nature lovers and adventurous travelers.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684685990</id>
    <title>Boac Cathedral </title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>Built as a fortress in 1792, the Boac Cathedral became a relevant part of the Marinduqueños colorful history and culture since its construction in the Spanish era. The locals used it as a hiding place during a Moro attack in the 1800s. Consequently, it also served as the venue of the blessing of the Philippine Revolutionary flag in 1899.&#13;
&#13;
Upon entering the church, you will see beautifully carved doors and exterior walls that are made of red bricks. Inspired by Hispanic Gothic architecture, the cathedral’s interior and ceiling showcase simple yet intricate carvings. Because of its cultural and historical significance, it is considered one of the must-see Boac Marinduque spots.&#13;
&#13;
The cathedral’s grand facade and bell tower are composed of adobe stones and rough terra cotta. There are also massive buttresses that resemble the UNESCO World Heritage Site of Paoay Church in Ilocos. </content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684686004</id>
    <title>Tres Reyes Islands</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>Another postcard-worthy spot in Marinduque, the Treys Reyes Islands, is nestled off the coast of Gasan municipality. The jump-off point is at Gasan port where tour boats await passengers before heading to the neighboring Three Kings islets, namely Melchor, Gaspar, and Baltazar.&#13;
&#13;
The largest among the three is Gaspar Island, a tranquil paradise with crystal clear waters and fine white sand. Next is Melchor Island, featuring rock formations covered in lush vegetation. Lastly, the Baltazar Island offers a lovely haven for those seeking a secluded spot to laze on the sand and lounge in beach cabanas.&#13;
&#13;
Among the must-see spots on Baltazar Island is a hilltop lighthouse, which was built during the American colonial period in 1910. Before capping off your island escapade, don’t forget to see the unique rock formations at Kulapnit Cave. Then, drop by the Kay Bungo Cave, a historical site where elongated skulls were found. </content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684686027</id>
    <title>Mount Malindig</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>Majestically standing on an elevation of 1,157 meters above sea level, Mount Malindig is a must-visit Buenavista Marinduque tourist spot and is considered the highest peak in the province. It is a stratovolcano situated at the island’s southern tip and west side of the Bondoc Peninsula on Luzon Island.&#13;
Because of its vast landscape and thriving ecosystem, Mount Malindig is comparable to Mt. Banahaw and Mt. Makiling in Quezon and Laguna provinces of Southern Luzon. At the base of Mount Malindig lies a therapeutic sulfuric spring called the Malbog Sulfur Spring. Many locals and tourists flock here to experience the healing powers of the spring.&#13;
&#13;
Mount Malindig is a hike-friendly destination for mountaineers. Based on the Pinoy Mountaineer rating system, it has a difficulty level of 4, which requires a minor climb. Having a trail classification level 1 and 2, Mount Malinig has a well-established trail with somewhat rugged and steep paths.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684686054</id>
    <title>Bagumbungan Cave </title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>For those who like to experience spelunking in the Philippines, you can check out one of Marinduque’s subterranean wonders, the Bagumbungan Cave. It is often compared to Sumaguing Cave in Sagada because of its stalactites and stalagmites in impressive shapes and forms. Bagumbungan Cave is a great spelunking spot that features magnificent rock formations. &#13;
The jump-off point is at the Santa Cruz town where the cave is located. At the cave’s entrance, there is a pathway leading down the waist-deep underground river basin. To get there, you have to pass through slippery surfaces and narrow passages. The path gets a bit more challenging as you slide down the muddy paths and squeeze yourself between huge rocks.&#13;
&#13;
Bagumbungan Cave is 1.9KM long and has a beginner-friendly trail, ideal for those who are new to spelunking. Some parts of the cave are off-limits for tourists. It remains largely unexplored, making it a wonderland for adventure seekers out there.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684686075</id>
    <title>Poctoy White Beach </title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>Among the well-known attractions in Marinduque is the Poctoy White Beach, a long stretch of fine white sand lined with palm trees in the coastal municipality of Torrijos. Surrounding the powdery beach are crystal clear waters that are ideal for swimming and kayaking. There are beachfront huts and cottages with chairs and tables, perfect for spending laidback afternoons on the beach.&#13;
&#13;
Underneath the crystalline waters is a sight to behold for scuba divers. The Poctoy Underwater Museum showcases giant Moryon monuments, which symbolize Marinduqueños iconic Moriones festival that happens every Holy Week.&#13;
&#13;
Aside from being one of the idyllic beaches in Marinduque, Poctoy White Beach remains to be among the emerging Torrijos Marinduque tourist spots. It attracts many local and international travelers annually because of its pristine shores and panoramic sunset views glowing over the horizon.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684686092</id>
    <title>Maniwaya Island </title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>Among all the famed destinations in Marinduque, Maniwaya Island should be on top of your bucket list. It is one of the several islands in Marinduque dotting Santa Cruz town that can rival famous white-sand beaches in the Philippines. Along the shoreline, you can find budget-friendly resorts and glamping cottages that resemble those in Bali, Indonesia. Off the northern coast of the island is Palad Sandbar, a patch of white sand that unravels and seemingly invites you to dip into the surrounding crystal blue waters. The best time to visit the sandbar is in the morning, as the whole strip of white sand appears during low tide. The stunning backdrop of the palm-fringed shores and turquoise-colored waters is perfect for taking Instagrammable selfies and group photos. To cap off your trip, don’t miss out on the chance to witness the best view of the sunset on Maniwaya Island.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684686121</id>
    <title>Kawa-Kawa Falls</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>After finishing your quest to explore Bagumbungan Cave, I’d say that the perfect way to replenish your strength is by taking a relaxing bath at Kawa-Kawa Falls. This small waterfall stands at only about 15 feet but with a deep and wide pool where visitors can dive and swim all they want!&#13;
&#13;
The crystal clear waters cascading down the beautiful rock formations of Kawa-Kawa Falls will surely help you soothe and regenerate your body to prepare for another adventure. Well, the fall is indeed a precious gem worth visiting, so I hope you don’t mind a little bit more hiking and trekking!</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684686358</id>
    <title>Butterfly Garden</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>Up next, did you know that Marinduque is also home to the place heralded as the “Butterfly Capital of the Philippines”? Yup! Gasan, Marinduque famously got its nickname for providing 85% of our country’s butterfly and pupa exports. This is the main reason why butterfly farming became the number one source of livelihood in Gasan, which they are absolutely most proud of! So, are you ready?&#13;
Our next destination is no other than the famous Gasan Butterfly Garden which houses thousands of species of butterflies as well as colorful plants and flowers. Visiting Gasan truly promises a visually satisfying experience for everyone whether you’re a nature lover or not. All you have to do is to open your eyes and witness some of nature’s unbelievable creations. That’s it!</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684686399</id>
    <title>Luzon Datum</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>Well, we’ve mentioned that Marinduque is regarded as the “Heart of the Philippines”, right? Aside from being shaped like a heart geographically, Marinduque is also positioned at the center of our country where the heart should be ideally located. And to prove our claim even more, why don’t we visit the iconic Luzon Datum or Station Balanacan which is acknowledged by NAMRIA? Yup! This stone marker is placed on top of a hill called Mt. Mataas and is officially recognized by NAMRIA as the Luzon Datum of 1911.&#13;
&#13;
In other words, this particular stone marker remains to be the primary geodetic origin or reference of all geological surveys in the entire Philippines! I gotta say, that’s a pretty mind-blowing fact right there.&#13;
Oh, and aside from admiring this historical landmark, visitors can also have the chance to enjoy the picturesque scenery on top of Mt. Mataas where you can clearly see the beauty of lush mountains and the breathtaking horizon from afar. So be sure to take amazing photos!</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684686428</id>
    <title>Bathala Cave</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>Tucked deep within Barangay Ipil in Sta. Cruz, Marinduque is a mystical cave that’s undeniably worthy of its name. Bathala Cave became popular because locals believe that a lot of mysteries and supernatural powers are being held inside the complex cave system. It is said that there are a total of seven caves inside Bathala Cave but only four are allowed to be explored due to safety reasons. The first one is the Simbahan Cave which incredibly resembles that of an ancient church due to the beautiful rock formations that seemingly create an altar. Next, is the Python Cave which is guarded by a python and thousands of bats hanging from the ceiling. The Underground Cave on the other hand is said to keep a breathtaking underground river. Finally, the fourth cave is known as the Cemetery Cave because several buried remains of men were found inside it. It is believed that these are the remains of World War II soldiers.&#13;
&#13;
Enchanted or not, Bathala Cave is indeed a haven for trekking and spelunking enthusiasts out there. The challenge is up for every brave adventurer out there so be sure not to back down!</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684686445</id>
    <title>Mang Iliol’s Sunflower Farm</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>After conquering the challenge of exploring Bathala Cave, why don’t we relax for a bit and enjoy another light and refreshing attraction in Marinduque? Yup! Our next destination is no other than Mang Iliol’s Sunflower Garden. This is one of the newest trending attractions in Marinduque which definitely catches the attention of many tourists. It’s a perfect place to take some awesome pictures as a remembrance of your Marinduque getaway as well. Oh, and of course, the Sunflower Garden is also a beautiful addition to your mandatory social media post!</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684686459</id>
    <title>St. Joseph Parish</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>This beautiful church is situated on top of a hill so aside from the beautiful architecture and interior of the church, visitors are also treated to a breathtaking panoramic view of Gasan.&#13;
There’s a steep climb before you can reach the top of the hill where St. Joseph Parish is located but the challenge is absolutely worth it in the end! There’s also a place regarded as the Meditation Garden within the church which is a perfect spot to quietly admire the scenery and even take awesome pictures. It’s definitely a perfect opportunity to offer our prayers and give thanks for another safe and memorable adventure!</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684686489</id>
    <title>Balanacan View Deck</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>It is located near the boundary of Brgy. Ino. The present view deck, which offers a 270-degree view of the northwestern portion of Mogpog, was reconstructedfromasingle storeygalvanized ironroofingintoa two-storeyconcreteslab view area.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684690566</id>
    <title>Balanacan Cove</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>This is one of the most ideal and secluded coves of the province that witnessed the long history of Marinduque. This location was chosen by the Spanish Admiralty as a construction and repair facility of the Spanish navy.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684690584</id>
    <title>Casa Real</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>This is a newly built replica of the old Spanish “Casa Real” that served as the administrative center of the province built on its original location. Today is it used by the Municipal Government of Boac as a multi-purpose building.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684690603</id>
    <title>Marinduque Museum</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>This National Museum–Marinduque branch displays the cultural past and arts exhibits of the province. </content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684690619</id>
    <title>Boac Ancestral Houses</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>This is a collection of more than a dozen Spanish and turn of the century ancestral houses scattered around the town center and was built by well- to- do families of Boac. The original architectures were preserved though today and the houses serve as mixed used facilities.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684690633</id>
    <title>Marinduque Provincial Capitol Building</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>The neo-classical Provincial Capitol Building was built in 1927. It consists of a two-storey concrete structure with four columns in front, was then rebuilt in 1947 after the war and is still being used today to house certain provincial offices including the office of the Governor. Fronting the building is the landscaped Capitol Park where the Centennial Monument, a concrete tableau of “Pugutan” and Bantayog Wika installed in recognition of Tagalog Marindukenyo proudly stand. </content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684690646</id>
    <title>Laylay Port</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>This served as the major port of Marinduque during the 19th century for ships with passengers and products plying the port from Boac to Manila and other ports. This was used extensively by local revolutionaries during the two phases of the Philippine revolution. Near the shore of Laylay in the vicinity of the old lighthouse was established in 1912 by USCGS a Magnetic Observation Station for measuring local variations in the earth’s magnetic field.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684690664</id>
    <title>Baliis Mountain View</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>This is located along the highest highway system of the province that covers Brgy. Bantay and Hinapulan, the area offers a scenic view of “above the clouds” or “sea of clouds” experience, and can be compared or is at par with views of Tagaytay or the Cordilleras. The Makulapnit, Bol, and Hinapulan river valleys that empty to the great Boac river are densely covered by low lying fog that can be observed in the early morning hours from 4AM to 8AM along the stretch of approximately 3-4 kilometers of this national highway.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684690680</id>
    <title>Haynon Hills </title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>These undulating hills have been utilized as pasture land and the site offers a relaxing view of scattered clamps of grassy and hilly terrain of different heights and elevation that turn color brown during summer months, due to the dry grasslands, acquiring a title of “Chocolate Hills of Haynon” but turns green during rainy season.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684690717</id>
    <title>Sta. Cruz Church</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>The church is one of the two oldest churches in the province. Like Boac Cathedral, it is surrounded by high protected walls. The church’s main attraction is its well-preserved retablo altar, its pulpit and original ceilings.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684690742</id>
    <title>Ungab Rock Formation</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>Check out one of the most iconic natural landmarks of Marinduque province. This rock formation, created from years of erosion, includes one part resembling a land bridge that connects to the sea. The waters here are clear and you can even spot colorful reef fish swimming about.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684690763</id>
    <title>Palad Sand Bar </title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>An exciting place of unique splendor where the tidal fluctuations commands the availability to visitors. An immaculate stretch of crushed coral sands in the middle of the sea appears only during low tides and is a must-see attraction</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684690783</id>
    <title>Pulang Lupa Historical Park</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>Historical shrine to one of two victorious battles won by Filipinos against the Americans during the Philippine-American War in Marinduque. September 15. 1900 was when Marinduqueños defeated the US troops.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684690821</id>
    <title>Poctoy Underwater Museum</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>Poctor Underwater Museum is near the Poctoy White Beach. It’s a man-made attraction set on a natural setting. When you dive here, you’ll find a statue of the iconic Morion.&#13;
&#13;
The project was realized through the initiative of Cong. Lord Allan Velasco together with Marinduque drivers.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684690964</id>
    <title>AMOINGON BEACH</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>If you like gazing at corals and colorful schools of fish rather than swimming and grilling, then you shouldn’t miss Amoingon Beach in Marinduque. Its waters are so teeming with marine life that many would call it the snorkeling capital of Marinduque. Still, if you’re not a fan of marine life or anything like that, you can still have fun above the clear shallow waters of Amoingon Beach. Get some fresh air and sunshine outdoors, or rent the nearest transient house and inhale the smell of the sea every morning while jogging.&#13;
&#13;
Amoingon Beach is located in Boac, mainland Marinduque and is accessible from either Santa Cruz of Mogpog via buses or longer jeepney rides.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684691239</id>
    <title>Natangco Islet</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>Natangco is an eight-hectare islet with a short stretch of powdery white sand that gradually slopes into the sea. Visitors are advised to bring water and food including tents for nature trips. Marine enthusiasts and scuba divers will find Natangco islet a haven with waters teeming with corals and marine life such as moorish idols, butterfly fishes, and an occasional sightings of manta rays, marlins, etc. </content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684691316</id>
    <title>Costa Celina Beach</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>Torrijos is a rustic town in Marinduque overflowing with spectacular white sand beaches guaranteed to amaze even the most travelled adventurer, and probably the best of these is Costa Celina. The closeness to nature one feels while being here has made it a prime destination for those who are looking for that one place where they can just relax and just revel in peace this haven has to offer.  &#13;
&#13;
Located in Sitio Talisay, Brgy. Bonliw, flanked by cliffs on both sides, Costa Celina is among the favorite dive spots in Marinduque. It is approximately 40 meters from the shore, with an undersea wall rich in diverse marine ecosystems teeming with flora and fauna.</content>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1684691343</id>
    <title>Battle of Paye Marker</title>
    <author>Vince Pelaez</author>
    <date>May/21/2023</date>
    <content>Battle of Paye Marker is located in Boac, Marinduque, Philippines.&#13;
&#13;
 &#13;
&#13;
This is another marker that serves as a reminder of the battle on July 31, 1900 between the Filipinos and the Americans. Despite inferior weapons, the Filipinos defeated the Americans.</content>
  </blog>
</blogs>
